Inventory of the M. King Hubbert papers, 1847-1990
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
M. King Hubbert papers
1847-1990
Hubbert, M. King (Marion King), 1903-
01238
104.00 cubic ft.
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Collection contains correspondence; lectures and class notes on physics and geology; publications and reprints; extensive research notes and subject files; glass negatives; maps & charts; and miscellaneous artifacts of this geophysicist.
Biography of M. King Hubbert
Marion King Hubbert (1903-1989) was born in central Texas and studied geology and physics at the University of Chicago. He received a Ph.D. from that institution in 1937. He taught geology and geophysics at Columbia University for ten years beginning in 1931. He served as senior analyst of world mineral resources on the Board of Economic Warfare during World War II. From 1943 to 1964 he worked for Shell Oil in Houston. After leaving Shell he became research geophysicist with the U.S. Geological Survey. He continued to teach, as a visiting professor, at various times at Stanford University and at the University of California, Berkeley. He was also a prolific author of scientific articles.
Scope and Content
Collection contains 61 boxes of correspondence (1943-1989) with colleagues on his research interests and teaching; lectures and class notes on physics and geology; publications and reprints; extensive research notes and subject files; glass negatives; maps & charts; and miscellaneous artifacts.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no other known archival collections created by M. King Hubbert at the date of processing.
Access Terms
Geology--Research.; Geology--Study and teaching (Higher).; Geophysics--Research.; Geophysics--Study and teaching (Higher).;;; Maps.; Geologists.; Geophysicists.
Education; Colleges and Universities; Science
Container List
- Correspondence, 1943-1989; Series I.
  Boxes 1-60, 60A
  - control file; M.J. Marek, copies of outgoing correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - M.J. Marek, copies of outgoing correspondence, 1950-1959 (Box 2)
  - M.J. Marek, copies of outgoing correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 3)
  - M.J. Marek, copies of outgoing correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 4)
  - copies of outgoing correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 5)
  - Cosmos club, corr. & chronological copies, cumulative reading file, general, first reading file, desk chronology, 1963-1969 (Box 6)
  - desk chronology, daily reading files, cosmos club forum, reading files, 1969-1973 (Box 7)
  - reading files, 1974-1976 (Box 8)
  - Applications - Building, 1946-1958 (Box 9)
  - supporting documentation: Company - Exploitation, 1944-1958 (Box 10)
  - Exploitation Engineering - Geology (Structural), 1946-1958 (Box 11)
  - Geophysical - Invitations, 1943-1959 (Box 12)
  - Journal of Geology - Pressure, 1944-1958 (Box 13)
  - Recommendation (letters of) - Theory, 1944-1959 (Box 14)
  - Underground - University, 1944-1959 (Box 15)
  - University of California - Willis (David G.), 1946-1959 (Box 16)
  - Personal files, 1943-1958 (Box 17)
  - Personal files, 1951-1957 (Box 18)
  - Personal files; Acknowledgment - Biographical, 1943-1958 (Box 19)
  - Book Reviews - Correspondence, general, 1959-1961 (Box 20)
  - Employment - Recommendation, 1951-1961 (Box 21)
  - Requests - Societies; American - Planned, 1959-1961 (Box 22)
  - Scientific - Visitors, 1959-1961 (Box 23)
  - Acknowledgment, 1962 (Box 23)
  - File - Visitors, 1962 (Box 24)
  - Alaska - Geographers, 1963-1967 (Box 25)
  - American Geological - American Institute, 1963-1967 (Box 26)
  - American Institute of Mining, Mechanical - Geodesy, 1963-1967 (Box 27)
  - Geological - Itineraries, 1963-1967 (Box 28)
  - Lectures - National (Aeronautics), 1963-1967 (Box 29)
  - National (Committee) - United Nations (Conference), 1963-1967 (Box 30)
  - United Nations (References) - Water, 1963-1967 (Box 31)
  - Water; Cumulative (correspondence) - Miscellaneous, 1963-1967 (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous - Old file indexes; Book - General, 1963-1967 (Box 33)
  - General -R. Rose; Acknowledgment -Society; current corresp.: “A” misc. - American (Assoc. Petrol. Geologists), 1963-1985 (Box 34)
  - current: American (Assoc. of Petrol. Geologists Mbrship) - Association (Engineering Geologists), 1970-1989 (Box 35)
  - current: “B” misc. - Borg, Dr. Iris Y, 1970-1986 (Box 36)
  - current: British - Club of Rome (1981), 1970-1985 (Box 37)
  - current: Club of Rome (1978) - “D” misc, 1951-1984 (Box 38)
  - current: Dahlberg, Eric - Ellison, Samuel, 1969-1982 (Box 39)
  - current: Energy - Franssen, Herman, 1970-1984 (Box 40)
  - current: Freeman, Wm. - USGS (Branch of Oil & Gas), 1970-1989 (Box 41)
  - current: USGS (Science) - Handler, G., 1962-1987 (Box 42)
  - current: Harboe, Henrik - HEW, 1971-1982 (Box 43)
  - current: Health - Interior, 1971-1983 (Box 44)
  - current: International - Johnson, 1973-1984 (Box 45)
  - current: “K” misc - McCulloh, Thane, 1971-1982 (Box 46)
  - current: McCutchan, Charles - “N” misc, 1967-1985 (Box 47)
  - current: National - Office of Tech. Asses. (Dr. Steven Plotkin), 1951-1985 (Box 48)
  - current: Office of Tech. Asses. (US Nat. Gas) - Permission, 1971-1989 (Box 49)
  - current: Permission (to quote MKH) - Publishers, 1956-1985 (Box 50)
  - current: Publishing - Rockefeller, 1964-1983 (Box 51)
  - current: Role - S.E.G, 1969-1987 (Box 52)
  - current: Solar - Udall, Stewart, 1955-1986 (Box 53)
  - current: Udall, (nuclear radiation) - Voskuil, 1970-1983 (Box 54)
  - current: “W” misc. - Wilder, Jane, 1964-1987 (Box 55)
  - current: Willis, David G. - Zettel, JH, 1969-1988 (Box 56)
  - 1977-1987 chron.: January 1 1977- December 28 1981, 1977-1981 (Box 57)
  - 1977-1987 chron.: January 5 1982 - December 29 1987, 1982-1987 (Box 58)
  - Reading files chron.; telephone calls, 1976-1988 (Box 59)
  - telephone log, telephone records, yearly calendar, mail log, 1964-1978 (Box 60)
  - [misc. corr.] A- U, undated (Box 60A)
- Lectures and Class Notes, 1925-1985; Series II.
  - Lectures, Subseries 1.
    Boxes 61-66
    - L: A.A.P.G. -Butter & Cheese, 1974-1983 (Box 61)
    - L: California - E.S.C. Kings Point, 1975-1985 (Box 62)
    - L: E.S.C. (O.P.M.) - Drexell, 1973-1983 (Box 63)
    - L: Electrical - Los Alamos, 1974-1982 (Box 64)
    - L: M.I.T. - Wisconsin, state, 1974-1982 (Box 65)
    - L: Wisconsin, Univ. - Yale, 1974-1982 (Box 66)
    - L: Lectures: Stanford, 1962-1969 (Box 66)
  - Lectures and Class Notes, Subseries 2.
    Boxes 66-71
    - Physics & Underground, 1963 (Box 66)
    - Physics: Stanford - Ground Water Hydrology, 1961-1969 (Box 67)
    - Physics - Society, 1950s-1973 (Box 68)
    - class notes: Chemical - Physics, 1925-1967 (Box 69)
    - class notes: Petrography - Physics, 1925-1962 (Box 70)
    - class notes: Theoretical - Vector, 1929-1980 (Box 71)
  - Figures and Slides, Subseries 3.
    Boxes 71-75
    - fig.: Physics - Senate (Box 71)
    - fig.: Senate Report - Degree - Concerning Nuclear, mid, 1974-1967 (Box 72)
    - fig.: Misc. - Statement: original, mid, 1974-1979 (Box 73)
    - L: References, Statements, Manuscript, Corresp., Commemorative Congress (U.S. Energy), 1974-1975 (Box 74)
    - L: Energy Resources, paper, 1945-1969 (Box 75)
  - Manuscripts, Subseries 4.
    Boxes 75-76, 76A
    - M: Application - Strength (Box 75)
    - M: Strength - Techniques, 1945-1969 (Box 76)
    - misc., 1983, 1986, undated (Box 76A)
- Personal Files, 1911-1990; Series III.
  - General, Subseries 1.
    Boxes 77-78
    - Background: (not sorted); (misc. unsorted), 1956-1976 (Box 77)
    - (misc. unsorted), 1950-1990 (Box 78)
  - Awards/Honors, Subseries 2.
    Boxes 78-83
    - misc., mainly A - C (Box 78)
    - misc., mainly C- H, 1972-1989 (Box 79)
    - misc. awards/honors mainly H-V; misc. personal files (Education, Genealogy, Pictures), 1911-1988 (Box 80)
    - misc. appointment books, expense accounts, notebooks, mid 1950s-late 1980s (Box 81)
    - misc. Who’s who files, clippings, correspondence material sent to Hubbert, 1960s, undated (Box 82)
    - photographs (Box 83)
  - Interview Transcript, Subseries 3.
    Box 83A
    - transcript of oral history interview for American Institute of Physics, 1989 (Box 83A)
- Publications and Reprints, 1920s-1980s; Series IV.
  Boxes 84-102
  - misc. publications, 1934-1983 (Box 84)
  - misc. publications, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 85)
  - misc. abstracts & publications, 1930-1985 (Box 86)
  - misc. publications, 1927-1921 (Box 87)
  - misc. publications, 1960s-1970s (Box 88)
  - misc. publications, 1950s-1970s (Box 89)
  - misc. publications, 1940s-1950s (Box 90)
  - “Role of Fluid Pressure” by Laubscher, 1962 (Box 91)
  - misc. publications, 1940s-1970s (Box 92)
  - misc. publications, papers, 1970s-1980s (Box 93)
  - misc. publications, notebook, 1950s-1970s (Box 94)
  - misc. abstracts, copies of slides, notes, publications, 1940s-1980s (Box 95)
  - misc. publications, 1960s-1980s (Box 96)
  - misc. publications, 1930s-1970s (Box 97)
  - misc. books, publications, 1920s-1970s (Box 98)
  - misc. publications, photo prints & negatives, 1940s-1950s (Box 99)
  - printer’s proofs, 1950s (Box 100)
  - printer’s proofs, 1940s-1950s (Box 101)
  - printer’s proofs, photographs, 1856-1948, undated (Box 102)
- Research, 1847-1988; Series V.
  Boxes 103-115
  - Air shot - Degree, 1951-1982 (Box 103)
  - Degree - Energy, 1921-1972 (Box 104)
  - Energy (geothermal) - Energy (resources), 1940s-1981 (Box 105)
  - Energy (resources) - Fluid, 1937-1981 (Box 106)
  - Fluid potential - Hydraulics, 1940s-1978 (Box 107)
  - Hydrodynamic - Magnetic, 1951-1971 (Box 108)
  - Mineral - Notes, 1940-1972 (Box 109)
  - Nuclear - Oil, 1938-1971 (Box 110)
  - Oil - Petroleum, 1938-1971 (Box 111)
  - Petroleum - Publications, 1944-1988 (Box 112)
  - Radio - Referee, 1942-1982 (Box 113)
  - Reserves - Structural, 1947-1977 (Box 114)
  - Structural - World, 1847-1972 (Box 115)
- Subject Files, 1856-1989; Series VI.
  Boxes 116-178
  - Abrahamson - Alaska, 1964-1975 (Box 116)
  - Alaska - American (A.A.P.G.), 1951-1973 (Box 117)
  - A.A.P.G., 1952-1974 (Box 118)
  - A.A.P.G. - A.I.M.E, 1947-1985 (Box 119)
  - A.I.M.E. - A.M.S.O.C., 1943-1972 (Box 120)
  - A.P.G. - Atoms, 1943-1978 (Box 121)
  - Atwater - Birch, 1959-1980 (Box 122)
  - Biswas - Cameron, 1959-1987 (Box 123)
  - Canada - Coalinga, 1939-1987 (Box 124)
  - Coalinga - Commoner, B., 1963-1985 (Box 125)
  - Commoner, B. - Cook, Dr. E., 1950-1976 (Box 126)
  - Cook, E., 1970-1982 (Box 127)
  - Cornell - Darcy’s Law, 1940s-1984 (Box 128)
  - Darcy’s - Desert, 1856-1987 (Box 129)
  - Desert - Earthquakes, 1949-1984 (Box 130)
  - Earthquakes - Energy (crisis), 1956-1989 (Box 131)
  - Energy (domestic) - Energy (energy), 1948-1975 (Box 132)
  - Energy (energy) - Energy (natural), 1948-1980s (Box 133)
  - Energy (natural), 1950-1987 (Box 134)
  - Energy (natural), 1958-1988 (Box 135)
  - Energy (1971 International) - Energy Resources (energy), 1948-1988 (Box 136)
  - Energy Resources (energy) - Energy Resources (oil), 1969-1983 (Box 137)
  - Energy Resources (of the earth) - Energy resources (U.S.), 1961-1976 (Box 138)
  - Energy (scramble) - Environment, 1955-1980 (Box 139)
  - Environmental - Fossil, 1963-1988 (Box 140)
  - Fossils - Geography, 1958-1986 (Box 141)
  - Geologic - G.S.A., 1946-1985 (Box 142)
  - G.S.A. - Geophysical, 1930s-1966 (Box 143)
  - Geophysical - Ground, 1930s-1987 (Box 144)
  - Ground - History, 1947-1987 (Box 145)
  - History - Hydraulic, 1946-1972 (Box 146)
  - Hydrodynamic - I.I.A.S.A., 1950-1987 (Box 147)
  - International - Ivanhoe, L.P., 1947-1987 (Box 148)
  - Ivanhoe - Lithium, 1963-1987 (Box 149)
  - Llewellyn, R. - McCulloch, T., 1956-1987 (Box 150)
  - McKelvey - Meyerhof, A.A., 1947-1981 (Box 151)
  - Michigan - Mohole, 1957-1979 (Box 152)
  - Nakazawa - N.A.S., 1961-1978 (Box 153)
  - N.A.S., 1961 (Box 154)
  - N.A.S. - N.S.F., 1945-1975 (Box 155)
  - N.S.F. - Nuclear, 1952-1976 (Box 156)
  - Nuclear - Oil, 1953-1973 (Box 157)
  - Oil - Petroleum, 1950-1981 (Box 158)
  - Petroleum - Power, 1951-1980 (Box 159)
  - Price - Radioactive, 1927-1985 (Box 160)
  - Radioactive, 1955-1965 (Box 161)
  - Radioactive - Resources & Man, 1954-1987 (Box 162)
  - Resources & Man, 1963-1982 (Box 163)
  - Resources & Man, 1967-1971 (Box 164)
  - Resources & Man, 1964-1969 (Box 165)
  - Resources & Man, 1966-1969 (Box 166)
  - Resources - Rock, 1953-1975 (Box 167)
  - Role, 1959-1966 (Box 168)
  - Rollover - Savannah, 1960-1976 (Box 169)
  - Scanlan - Sinclair, 1964-1979 (Box 170)
  - Smalley - Stanford, 1946-1989 (Box 171)
  - Stansbury - Symonds, 1960-1988 (Box 172)
  - Syracuse - Theory, 1939-1973 (Box 173)
  - Theory - U.S. Coast, 1945-1979 (Box 174)
  - U.S. Energy - Volume, 1943-1987 (Box 175)
  - Volume - Waste, 1943-1982 (Box 176)
  - Waste - Wisconsin, 1963-1983 (Box 177)
  - Work - Wyoming, 1964-1983 (Box 178)
- Travel, 1944-1963; Series VII.
  Boxes 179-182
  - (chron.) September 1944 -December 10, 1954, 1944-1954 (Box 179)
  - (chron.) April 4, 1955 - December 10, 1958, 1955-1958 (Box 180)
  - (chron.) January 27, 1959 - August 23, 1961, 1959-1961 (Box 181)
  - (chron.) September 5, 1961 - December 10, 1963, 1961-1963 (Box 182)
- Glass Negatives and Glass Positives (Lantern Slides), Series VIII.
  - 8 boxes (Box 183-190)
- Maps & Charts, Series IX.
  - 50 map tubes
- Artifacts, Series X.
  - 2 boxes
- Oversize Material, Series XI.
  - 4 boxes
- Additional Container Lists
  The American Heritage Center is in the process of converting its older container lists to a more accessible format. This link is to an older version of a container list.
  - Link to Accessioning Worksheet (PDF)